So the last, we only have four more lectures left,
快期末了 我们只剩下四次课了
and what Professor Demaine and I have decided to do
Demaine教授和我决定了
is give two series of lectures on sort of advanced topics.
接下来的课会介绍两个高级课题
So, today and Wednesday we're going to
那么 我们准备在今天和星期三
talk about parallel algorithms,
讨论并行算法
algorithms where you have more than one processor
这种算法会用到多个处理器
whacking away on your problem.
并行地解决问题
And this is a very hot topic right now
这个课题最近非常火
because all of the chip manufacturers
因为现在的那些芯片制造商
are now producing so-called multicore processors
都在生产所谓的多核处理器
where you have more than one processor per chip.
每个芯片都有多于一个处理器
So, knowing something about that is good.
所以 多了解这些知识有好处
The second topic we're going to cover
我们想讲的第二个课题是
is going to be caching,
关于缓存的算法
and how you design algorithms for systems with cache.
以及如何为有缓存机制的系统设计算法
Right now, we've sort of program to everything
目前来说 我们在编程时
as if it were just a single level of memory,
都只用了单一的一层内存
and for some problems
但对于某些问题
that's not an entirely realistic model.
这跟现实的模型不完全一样
You'd like to have some model
现实中你用到的模型
for how the caching hierarchy works,
需要考虑多级缓存怎么运作
and how you can take advantage of that.
以及怎么利用好多层缓存
And there's been a lot of research in that area as well.
这个领域人们也已经做了很多研究
So, both of those actually
其实 这两个课题
turn out to be my area of research.
都在我的研究范围内
So, this is actually fun for me.
我对这些东西很有爱
Actually, most of it's fun anyway.
实际上 大部分都很有趣
So, today we'll talk about parallel algorithms.
那么 我们今天讨论的是并行算法
And the particular topic, it turns out that
关于这个课题 实际上
there are lots of models for parallel algorithms,
我们有许多种不同的并行算法模型
and for parallelism.
和并行化模型
And it's one of the reasons that,
这样的原因是
whereas for serial algorithms,
对于串行算法而言
most people sort of have this basic model
人们一般只有一种基础模型
that we've been using.
也就我们用的那种
It's sometimes called a random access machine model,
它有时候被称为随机存取机器模型
which is what we've been using to analyze things,
我们之前的分析就是基于这个模型
whereas in the parallel space,
但是在并行的空间里
there's just a huge number of models,
还有很多其它的模型
and there is no general agreement
而且还没有一个共识
on what is the best model
认为哪一个才是最佳模型
because there are different machines
因为不同的模型
that are made with different configurations, etc.
它们有不同的构造
And people haven't, sort of, agreed on,
而且人们甚至还没确定
even how parallel machines should be organized.
并行模型应该如何组织
So, we're going to deal with a particular model,
那么 我们准备研究一种并行模型
which goes under the rubric of dynamic multithreading,
它是属于动态多线程的一种
which is appropriate for the multicore machines
适合用于多核机器中
that are now being built for shared memory programming.
它是为内存共享的编程而设计的
It's not appropriate for what's called
并不适用于所谓的
distributed memory programs particularly
分布式内存编程
because the processors are able to access things.
因为每个处理器都有访问内存的权限
And for those, you need more involved models.
对于其他的情况 你需要学习更多相关的模型
And so, let me start just by giving an example of
所以 让我们从一个简单的例子开始
how one would write something.
看看怎么写并行程序
I'm going to give you a program
我准备给你一个程序
for calculating the nth Fibonacci number in this model.
这是用来计算第n个斐波拉契数的模型
This is actually a really bad algorithm
其实我接下来要讲的
that I'm going to give you
是一个很差的算法
because it's going to be the exponential time algorithm,
因为它的复杂度是指数级的
whereas we know from week one or two that you can
然而我们在前两周就学会了
calculate the nth Fibonacci number in how much time?
计算Fibonacci数要花多少时间？
Log n time. So, this is two exponentials off of
log n的时间 节省了两个指数
what you should be able to get, OK, two exponentials off.
这才是你应该得到的结果 节省了两个指数
OK, so here's the code.
好的 下面是伪代码
OK, so this is essentially the pseudocode we would write.
好的 这个就是我们要写的伪代码
And let me just explain a little bit about,
我来解释一下
we have a couple of key words here we haven't seen before:
有几个关键词我们从没见过
in particular, spawn and sync.
特别是衍生(spawn)和同步(sync)
OK, so spawn, this basically says that
好的 这个衍生其实就是指
the subroutine that you're calling,
你正在调用一个子程序
you use it as a keyword before a subroutine,
你把衍生作为一个关键字加在子程序前
that it can execute at the same time as its parent.
这样它就能跟父程序同时执行
So here, what we say x equals spawn of fib of n minus one
这里 我们说 x=spawn fib(n-1)
we immediately go onto the next statement.
我们立刻转到下一语句
And now, while we're executing fib of n minus one,
现在当我们在计算fib(n-1)的时候
we can also be executing, now,
我们同时也在执行...
this statement which itself will spawn something off.
下面这条语句 它本身也会衍生子程序
OK, and we continue, and then we hit the sync statement.
好的 我们继续 然后我们碰到这个同步语句
And, what sync says is,
同步就是说
wait until all children are done.
等待至所有子程序完成
OK, so it says once you get to this point,
所以 一旦你运行到这里
you've got to wait until everything here has completed
你需要等到所有子程序完成后
before you execute the x plus y
才能继续执行这个 x+y
because otherwise you're going to
否则的话 你就要
try to execute the calculation
用还没算出来的x和y
of x plus y without having computed it yet.
来执行x+y这个运算
OK, so that's the basic structure.
好的 这就是它的基础结构
What this describes, notice in here we never said
这是说... 注意了 我们还未曾说过
how many processors or anything we are running on.
我们要用到多少处理器神马的
OK, so this actually is
好吧 这实际上
just describing logical parallelism
只是描述了并行的逻辑
——not the actual parallelism when we execute it.
而不是我们实际的并行化执行
And so, what we need is a scheduler to determine
所以 我们要用到一个调度器来决定
how to map this dynamically unfolding execution
如何把这个动态的 不断延伸的程序
onto whatever processors you have available.
映射到可用的处理器上
OK, and so today actually,
好的 那么今天实际上
we're going to talk mostly about scheduling.
我们会集中讲关于调度的内容
and then, next time we're going to talk about
然后下一次 我们就会讨论
specific application algorithms,
一些特定的应用算法
and how you analyze them.
以及如何去分析它们
So you can view the actual multithreaded computation.
那时 你们就能看到真真的多线程计算
If you take a look at the parallel instruction stream,
如果你看过并行指令流就知道
it's just a directed acyclic graph, OK?
它其实是一个有向非循环图
So, let me show you how that works.
那么 我来讲讲它是怎么工作的
So, normally when we have an instruction stream,
当我们有一个指令流
I look at each instruction being executed.
我观察正在运行的每一个指令
If I'm in a loop, I'm not looking at it as a loop.
即使是个循环 我也不把它当做循环来看
I'm just looking at
我只观察
the sequence of instructions that actually executed.
实际执行的指令序列
I can do that just as a chain.
我把它当成一个链来看
Before I execute one instruction,
在我执行一个指令之前
I have to execute the one before it.
我必须先执行完它前面的指令
Before I execute that,
在我执行这个之前
I've got to execute the one before it.
我已经执行完它前面的一条指令
At least, that's the abstraction.
至少 大概是这样的
If you've studied processors,
如果你研究处理器
you know that there are a lot of tricks there
你会知道有许多的小技巧
in figuring out instruction level parallelism,
来了解指令级别的并行机制
and how you can actually
以及你要如何
make that serial instruction stream
让原本串行的指令流
actually execute in parallel.
实际执行时变为并行
But what we are going to be mostly talking about
但是我们要集中讨论的
is the logical parallelism here,
是逻辑上的并行机制
and what we can do in that context.
以及在这个背景下 我们能做的事情
So, in this DAG, the vertices are threads,
那么 在这个DAG里 顶点代表的是线程
which are maximal sequences of instructions
所谓线程也就是最长的指令序列
not containing parallel control.
该序列中不包含任何并行控制
And by parallel control,
这个并行控制
I just mean spawn, sync,
我指的就是衍生和同步
and return from a spawned procedure.
还有从一个衍生的子程序返回
So, let's just mark the, so the vertices are threads.
所以 我们就把线程标记为顶点
So, let's just mark what the vertices are here,
那么 我们来标记这里的顶点
OK, what the threads are here.
这里有什么线程
So, when we enter the function here,
所以 当我们进入这个函数后
we basically execute up to the point where,
我们基本上就执行这里
basically, here, let's call that thread A
基本上 这里 我们称这个线程A
where we are just doing a sequential execution
是以序列顺序执行的
up to either returning
直到遇到返回为止
or starting to do the spawn, fib of n minus one.
或者是执行衍生指令fib(n-1)
So actually, thread A would include
所以实际上 线程A包含了
the calculation of n minus one right up to the point
到求n-1这一步为止的运算
where you actually make the subroutine jump.
也就是恰好在做子任务跳转前的一步
That's thread A.
这就是线程A
Thread B would be the stuff that you would do,
线程B执行的是
executing from fib of, sorry,
执行从fib到...不好意思
B would be from the...
那B就会从(这里)开始
We'd go up to the spawn.
上面其实是做到衍生这一步
So, we've done the spawn. I'm really looking at this.
我们已经做完了衍生的操作 A应该是到这儿
So, B would be up to the spawn of y.
所以 B是一直做到衍生y
OK, spawn of fib of n minus two to compute y,
把fib(n-2)衍生出来 算出y的值
and then we'd have essentially an empty thread.
现在 这里实际上是一个空线程
So, I'll ignore that for now, but really
我现在先忽略这个 实际上...
then we have...after the sync up to the point
接着 我们有...在做完同步后
that we get to the return of x plus y.
我们就取得x+y的返回值
So basically, we're just looking at
所以基本上 我们只是观察
maximal sequences of instructions that are all serial.
最长的串行指令序列
And every time I do a parallel instruction, OK,
而每一次执行并行指令时
a spawn or a sync, or return from it,
比如衍生 同步或从线程中返回
that terminates the current thread.
都会结束当前的线程
So we can look at that as a bunch of small threads.
那么 我们可以把这些看是一些小线程组合
So those of you who are familiar with threads
对于很熟悉线程的人来说
from Java threads, or POSIX threads, so-called P threads,
Java里面的线程或者POSIX线程 又叫P线程
those are sort of heavyweight static threads.
那些都是重量级的静态线程
This is a much lighter weight notion of thread,
这个就要轻量很多
OK, that we are using in this model.
这个模型用的是轻量级的
OK, so these are the vertices.
好的 顶点代表的是线程
And now, let me map out a little bit how this works,
现在 我来画一下这是怎么工作的
so we can see where the edges come from.
看看这些边是从哪里来的
So, let's imagine we're executing fib of four.
那么 假设我们在计算fib(4)
So, I'm going to draw a horizontal oval.
那么 我画一个水平的椭圆
That's going to correspond to the procedure execution.
这对应的是程序的执行
And, in this procedure,
那么在这个程序里
there are essentially three threads.
这里有三个线程
We start out with A,
我们从A开始
so this is our initial thread is this guy here.
所以 这就是我们初始的线程
And then, when he executes a spawn,
那么 当它要执行一个衍生
OK, he's going to execute a spawn,
好的 当它要衍生时
we are going to create a new procedure,
我们就创建一个新的程序
and he's going to execute a new A
接着它会在递归地在新程序里
recursively within that procedure.
执行一个新的A线程
But at the same time, we're also going to be,
但是同一时间 我们还能够
now, allowed to go on and execute B in the parent,
继续在父线程里执行B
we have parallelism here when I do a spawn.
所以这个衍生 就实现了并行机制
OK, and so there's an edge here.
好的 这里有一条边
This edge we are going to call a spawn edge,
这条边我们称它为衍生边
and this is called a continuation edge
然后 这一条是延续边
because it's just simply
因为这条边
continuing the procedure execution.
承接了一个程序内的执行
OK, now at this point, this guy, we now have two things
那现在这里 我们有两样东西
that can execute at the same time.
它们能够同时执行的
Once I've executed A,
一旦我执行了A
I now have two things that can execute.
我就有两样东西可以执行
OK, so this one,
那么 这一个
for example, may spawn another thread here.
举个例子 可能会衍生出另外一个线程
Oh, so this is fib of three, right?
噢 这个是fib(3) 对吧?
And this is now fib of two.
那这里是fib(2)
OK, so he spawns another guy here,
好的 它这里衍生出另外一个东西
and simultaneously, he can go on and execute B here,
同时 它可以继续执行这里的B
OK, with a continued edge.
好的 用一个延续边连接
And B, in fact, can also spawn at this point.
而实际上 B也能在这个点衍生
OK, and this is now fib of two also.
这个也是fib(2)
And now, at this point, we can't execute C yet here
那现在 在这个点上 我们还不能执行C
even though I've spawned things off.
即使我将所有线程都衍生完了
And the reason is because C won't execute
这是因为 还没轮到C
until we've executed the sync statement,
未执行同步指令之前 还不能执行C
which can't occur until A and B have both been executed,
要等到A和B都被执行完后 才开始同步
OK? So, he just sort of sits there waiting,
所以 C只能坐等A、B完事
OK, and a scheduler can't try to schedule him.
连调度器也带不起它
Or if he does, then nothing's going to happen here, OK?
就算要强行搞起 这里也是什么都做不了 是吧?
So, we can go on.
那么 我们继续
Let's see, here we could call fib of one.
我们来看 这里我们调用fib(1)
The fib of one is only going to
fib(1)只会执行
execute an A statement here.
一个A线程
OK, of course it can't continue here
当然 它这里已经没法继续
because A is the only thing,
因为只有一个A语句
when I execute fib of one, if we look at the code,
当我执行fib(1) 我们观察这代码
it never executes B or C. OK, and similarly here,
它也不会再执行B或者C 以此类推
this guy here to do fib of one.
这里也是执行fib(1)
And this guy, I guess, could execute a here of fib of one
而这个 它也会衍生出一个fib(1)
OK, and maybe now this guy calls his another fib of one,
这线程可能也调用一个fib(1)
and this guy does another one.
然后这里也调用另一个
This is going to be fib of zero, right?
这个将会变成fib(0) 对吧
I keep drawing that arrow to the wrong place.
我又把♂指错地方了
And now, once these guys return, well,
现在 一旦这些线程返回 好的
let's say these guys return here, I can now execute C.
比如它们返回到这里 我就可以执行C了
But I can't execute with them
但在这些都完成之前
until both of these guys are done, and that guy is done.
我是不能执行它的 这些都要完成才行
So, you see that we get
那么 你们会发现
a synchronization point here before executing C.
我们在C之前会遇到一个同步点
And then, similarly here,
然后 同样地
now that we've executed this and this,
现在我们已经执行了这个和这个
we can now execute this guy here.
我们现在可以执行这里的C了
And so, those returns go to there.
然后 这些都返回到这里了
Likewise here, this guy can now execute his C,
像是这个地方 这东西现在能执行C
and now once both of those are done,
一旦这两个都结束
we can execute this guy here.
我们就可以执行这里的C
And then we are done.
然后 我们就完成了
This is our final thread.
这是我们最后的线程
So, I should have labeled also that
那么 我这里应该标记下
when I get one of these guys here,
当我划出一条这样的边
that's a return edge.
它就是一条返回边
So, the three types of edges are spawn, return,
那么 边分为三类 有衍生 返回
and continuation. OK, and by describing it in this way,
以及延续 好的 通过这个方式来描述
I essentially get a DAG that unfolds.
我得到了一个展开的有向非循环图
So, rather than having just a serial execution trace,
那么 相对于只有串行的执行序列
I get something where I have
我还得到了一些别的东西
still some serial dependencies that
虽然它还保留了串行特性
some things has to be done before other things
例如 一项工作必须先完成才能做下一项
but there are also things that can be done at the same time.
但同时也有些工作能够同时完成
So how are we doing? Yeah, question?
那么我们怎么做? 有问题?
[Student]:......
[学生]:......
[Professor]:Is every spawn were covered by a sync,
是否每个衍生的线程都被同步操作覆盖到？
effectively, yeah, yeah, effectively.
是的 就是这样
There's actually a null thread that gets executed in there,
这里实际上还有一些空线程在执行
which I hadn't bothered to show.
我没有特地写出来
But yes, basically you would then not have any parallelism,
不过没错 但这基本上就不算并行了
OK, because you would spawn it off,
因为你衍生了它
but then you're not doing anything in the parent.
但在父线程里却什么也没做
So it's pretty much the same,
那就基本上
yeah, as if it had executed serially.
跟串行差不多
Yep, OK, so you can see that basically what we had here
好的 你们可以看到 我们这里得到的
in some sense is a DAG embedded in a tree.
其实就是一个嵌入树中的有向非循环图
OK, so you have a tree
你有这么一棵树
that's sort of the procedure structure,
它代表了程序执行的结构
but in there you have a DAG,
而这树里面有一个DAG
and that DAG can actually get to be pretty complicated.
实际上 这个DAG相当复杂
OK, now what I want to do is now that
那么 我现在想做的就是
we understand that we've got an underlying DAG,
既然知道底层有个DAG的存在
I want to switch to trying to study
我就想转而研究
the performance attributes of a particular DAG execution,
这一个DAG的各方面的执行性能
so looking at performance measures.
好 来看一下性能评估
So, the notation that we'll use is
那么 这里我们要用到的符号是
we'll let T_P be the running time
我们设T_P为任意程序运算——
of whatever our computation is on P processors.
——在P个处理器上的运行时间
OK, so, T_P is,
那么 T_P就等于
how long does it take to execute this on P processors
在P个处理器上执行一个程序所用的时间
Now, in general, this is not going to be
一般来说 T_P并不是
just a particular number,
一个固定的常数
because I can have different scheduling disciplines
因为我可以有不同的调度规则
would lead me to get numbers for T_P, OK?
使得T_P会取得不同的数值 对吧?
But when we talk about the running time,
但是当我们讨论运行时间时
we'll still sort of use this notation,
我们还是会使用这个符号
and I'll try to be careful as we go through to make sure
之后的讲解过程中 我会留个神
that there's no confusion about what that means in context.
确保上下文没有产生歧义
There are a couple of them,
而其中有几种T_P
though, which are fairly well defined.
已经被完整地定义过了
One is...Based on this.
一个是...最基本的一个
One is T_1. So, T_1 is the running time on one processor.
一个是T_1 那么 T_1就等于一个处理器上的运行时间
OK, so if I were to execute
好的 如果程序是由...
this on one processor, you can imagine
一个处理器来执行 可想而知
it's just as if I had just got rid of the spawn and syncs
这就像是 我把所有的衍生和同步都去掉
and everything, and just executed it.
通通去掉 仅仅执行它
That will give me a particular running time.
这就会得到它的一个运行时间
We call that running time on one processor the work.
我们把一个处理器上的运行时间称为功
It's essentially the serial time.
也就是串行运行时间
OK, so when we talk about the work of a computation,
好的 当我们谈到一次计算的功时
we just been essentially a serial running time.
我们实际上就是指它的串行运行时间
OK, the other measure that ends up being interesting
好的 另外一个有趣的评估值
is what we call T infinity.
我们把它设为T_∞
OK, and this is the critical pathlength,
好的 这是关键路径长度
OK, which is essentially the longest path in the DAG.
也就是指DAG中的最长路径
So, for example,
那么 举个例子
if we look at the fib of four in this example,
我们看看这个例子的fib(4)
it has T of one equal to,
它的T_1等于
so let's assume we have unit time threads.
我们先假设有单位时间的线程
I know they're not unit time, but let's just imagine,
我知道它们不是单位时间的 但先假设如此
for the purposes of understanding this,
为了帮助理解
that every thread costs me one unit of time to execute.
每个线程消耗一个单位时间来运行
What would be the work of this particular computation?
这样的话计算出的功会是多少?
17, right, OK,
17 对了
because all we do is just add up three, six,
因为我们做的加起来 3 6
nine, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.
然后9 12 13 14 15 16 17
So, the work is 17 in this case
所以这个例子里的功等于17
if it were unit time threads.
如果线程都是单位时间的
In general, you would add up how many
但一般来说 要求运行时间
instructions or whatever were in there.
应该是求一共运行了多少条指令
OK, and then T infinity is the longest path.
而T_∞则是最长路径的情况
So, this is the longest sequence.
那么 也就是最长指令序列
It's like, if you had an infinite number of processors,
就算你有无限的处理器可用
you still can't just do everything at once
你仍然没办法一下子把所有事情完成
because some things have to come before other things.
因为有些事情需要一个接一个地完成
But if you had an infinite number of processors,
但如果你有无数个处理器
as many processors as you want,
要多少有多少
what's the fastest you could possibly execute this?
那么你执行这个的最快速度会是多少?
A little trickier. Seven?
开动脑筋 7?
So, what's your seven?
那么 你的7怎么算的?
[Student]:......
[学生]:......
So, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
就是 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
eight, yeah, eight is the longest path.
8 对 8才是最长路径长度
So, the work and the critical path length, as we'll see,
那么 功和关键长度 我们将看到
are key attributes of any computation.
它们都是所有计算中的关键属性
And abstractly, and this is just for those
大致上说 噢这里要注明
if they're unit time threads.
如果它们是单位时间线程
OK, so we can use these two measures
那么 我们可以使用这两种方法
to derive lower bounds on T_P
来测量出T_P的下界
for P that fall between one and infinity,
当P处在1和无穷之间时
Ok?
对吧?
OK, so the first lower bound we can derive is that
好的 我们第一个推导出来的下界是
T_P has got to be at least T_1 over P.
T_P最小等于T_1/P
OK, so why is that a lower bound? Yeah?
为什么这个是下界?
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Professor]：But if I have P processors,
但如果我有P个处理器
[Professor]：and, OK, and why would I have this lower bound?
好吧 为什么我会有这个下界?
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Professor]：OK, yeah, you've got the right idea.
好的 你的想法是对的
So, but can we be a little bit more articulate about it?
但关于这个我们要说得更清楚一点
So, that's right, so you want to use all of processors.
没错 你希望用到所有的处理器
If you could use all of processors,
如果你能用上所有的处理器
why couldn't I use all the processors,
为什么即使用上所有处理器
though, and have T_P be less than this?
都没法让T_P比这个更小?
Why does it have to be at least as big as T_1 over P?
为什么它至少等于T_1/P
I'm just asking for a little more precision in the answer.
我想要更加准确的说法
You've got exactly the right idea,
你已经知道怎么做了
but I need a little more precision
但我需要更准确一点
if we're going to persuade the rest of the class
来说服班上的其他同学
that this is the lower bound.
这个就是下界
Yeah?
嗯?
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Professor]：Yeah, that's another way of looking at it.
是的 你确实可以这样看
If you were to serialize the computation, OK,
如果你把所有的计算串行化
so whatever things you execute on each step,
无论你每一步都执行了什么语句
you do P of them, and so if you serialized it,
你都要执行P次 如果把程序串行化的话
somehow then it would take you P steps
你就相当于要用P步
to execute one step of a P way,
才能完成P核的一步执行
a machine with P processors.
P核也就是P个处理器
So then, OK, yeah?
所以说 对吧?
OK, maybe a little more precise.
好的 稍微详细了一点
There?
那位帅哥?
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Professor]：Yeah, good, so let me just state this a little bit.
很好 让我把这个讲清楚吧
So, P processors, so what are we relying on?
如果有P个处理器 我们怎么利用它们?
P processors can do, at most, P work in one step,
P个处理器每一步最多能做P个功
right? So, in one step they do at most P work.
对吧？ 每一步它们最多只能做P的功
They can't do more than P work.
再多就做不了了
And so, if they can do at most P work in one step,
所以 如果它们每一步做功都能达到最大值P
then if the number of steps was, in fact,
而且实际运行的步数
less than T_1 over P,
要小于T_1/P的
they would be able to do more than T_1 work in P steps.
它们才能够在P步中做大于T_1的功
And, there's only T_1 work to be done.
但这里只需要做T_1的功
OK, I just stated that
好吧 我这个解释
almost as badly as all the responses I got.
就跟你们给我的解释一样水
OK, P processors can do,
好的 P个处理器可以
at most, P work in one step, right?
在一步中做最多P的功 对吧？
So, if there's T_1 work to be done,
如果这里需要做T_1的功
the number of steps is
执行的步数
going to be at least T_1 over P, OK?
至少等于T_1/P 是吧？
There we go. OK, it wasn't that hard.
我们继续 好的 其实不难
It's just like, I've got a certain amount of,
它就是说 我有一定数目的功
I've got T_1 work to do.
我有T_1的功要做
I can knock off, at most, P on every step.
如果我每一步最多能做P的功
How many steps? Just divide.
要做多少步  除一下就知道了
OK, so it's going to have to be at least that amount.
所以T_P至少就是那么多
OK, good.
成功说懵了
The other lower bound is T_P
另外一个下界T_P
is greater than or equal to T infinity.
它大于等于T_∞
Somebody explain to me why that might be true. Yeah?
有人来解释下为什么这个成立？
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Prof]:Yeah, if you have an infinite number of processors
是的  如果你有无数个处理器
You also have... you have P.
你肯定也有P个处理器
So if you could do it in a certain amount of time with P,
如果用P个处理器 要一定的时间来处理
you can certainly do it in that time
你肯定也能在那段时间里
with an infinite number of processors.
用无限的处理器处理完
OK, this is in this model where, you know,
好的 这就是要介绍的模型
there is lots of stuff that this model doesn't model
这个模型还有很多东西没有模拟
like communication costs and interference,
比如说传输费用和接口
and all sorts of things. But it is simple model,
以及其它别的东西 它虽然是一个简单的模型
which actually in practice works out pretty well,
但实际运用起来也很好用
You're not going to be able
你是不可能
to do more work with P processors
用P个处理器做功
than you are with an infinite number of processors.
做得比无限个处理器还多
OK, so those are helpful bounds to understand
好的 这些下界能有助我们理解
when we are trying to make something go faster,
因为当我们要优化程序速度时
it's nice to know what you could possibly hope to achieve,
最好是弄清楚我们可以获得什么成果
OK, as opposed to beating your head against a wall,
以免你45度仰天泪流满面
how come I can't get it to go much faster?
问道：就只有这点速度吗？！
Maybe it's because one of these lower bounds is operating.
也许就是其中一个下界在作怪
OK, well, we're interested in how fast we can go.
好的 我们想知道怎样能运行得更快
That's the main reason for using multiple processors
你使用多处理器的主要原因
is you hope you're going to go faster
就是希望你比单处理器
than you could with one processor.
运行得更快
So, we define T_1 over T_P to be
那么 我们定义T_1/T_P
the speedup on P processors.
为P个处理器上的加速比
OK, so we say, how much faster is it
那我们问 究竟P个处理器
on P processors than on one processor?
比单处理器要快多少？
OK, that's the speed up. If T_1 over T_P is order P,
好的 这就是加速比 如果T_1/T_P属于P阶
we say that it's linear speedup.
我们就称它为线性加速
OK, in other words, why?
好的 为什么这么说？
Because that says that it means that
因为这表示
if I've thrown P processors at the job
如果我在一个任务上用了P个处理器
I'm going to get a speedup that's proportional to P.
我得到的速度提升与P成正比
OK, so when I throw P processors at the job
好的 当我用P个处理器处理任务时
and I get T_P, if that's order P,
我就有T_P  如果它是P阶的
that means that in some sense
这说明 某种程度上
my processors each contributed
每个处理器都贡献了
within a constant factor its full measure of support.
它最大性能内的一定量的支持
If this, in fact, were equal to P,
如果这个 实际上等于P的话
we'd call that perfect linear speedup.
我们可以称之为完美线性加速
OK, so but here we're looking at giving ourselves,
好的 但是这里 我们理论上
for theoretical purposes,
假设有
a little bit of a constant buffer here, perhaps.
再大一点的常量
If T_1 over T_P is greater than P,
如果说T_1/T_P大于P
we call that super linear speedup.
我们称之为超级线性加速
OK, so can somebody tell me,
好的 有人能告诉我
when can I get super linear speedup?
怎么才能得到超级线性加速吗？
When can I get super linear speed up?
什么时候我能得到超级线性加速？
Never. OK, why never?
永远不可能 有理 为什么？
[Student]：......
[学生]:...
Yeah, if we buy these lower bounds,
嗯 如果我们认同这些下界
the first lower bound there,
那里的第一个下界
it is T_P is greater than or equal to T_1 over P.
T_P大于等于T_1/P
And, if I just take T_1 over T_P,
如果我取T_1/T_P的话
that says it's less than or equal to P.
它是小于等于P的
So, this is never,
所以 它永远不可能
OK, not possible in this model.
好吧 对这个模型来说不可能
OK, there are other models
但还有其他的一些模型
where it is possible to get super linear speed up
有可能实现超级线性加速
due to caching effects, and things of that nature.
因为利用了类似缓存的机制
But in this simple model that we are dealing with,
但在这个简单的模型里
it's not possible to get super linear speedup.
我们无法得到超级线性加速
OK, not possible.
阿迪王都不可能
Now, the maximum possible speedup,
那可能的最大加速是多少？
given some amount of work
已知功的大小
and critical path length is what?
和关键路径的长度
What's the maximum possible speed up
在任意数量的处理器上能取得的
I could get over any number of processors?
最大的加速会是多少？
What's the maximum I could possibly get?
最大值可能是多少？
No, I'm saying, no matter how many processors,
不是 我是说 不管有多少处理器也好
what's the most speedup that I could get?
我能得到的最大加速是多少？
T_1 over T infinity, because this is the,
T_1/T_∞ 因为这个是...
so T_1 over T infinity is the maximum I could possibly get.
T_1/T_∞是我能得到的最大值
If I threw an infinite number of processors at the problem
好的 如果我拿无数个处理器来处理问题
that's going to give me my biggest speedup.
那我就能得到最大的加速
OK, and we call that the parallelism.
好的 我们称这个为并行化
OK, so that's defined to be the parallelism.
好的 这就是并行度的定义
So the parallelism of the particular algorithm is
一个算法的并行度 本质上就是
essentially the work divided by the critical path length.
功除以关键路径长度
Another way of viewing it is that
从另一种角度上看
this is the average amount of work
就是在关键路径上——
that can be done in parallel
可以并行地完成的——
along each step of the critical path.
平均分量的功
And, we denote it often by P bar.
我们定义它为P帽
So, do not get confused.
所以 别搞乱了
P bar does not have anything to do with P at some level.
其实P帽跟P没有什么关系
OK, P is going to be a
好的 这里的P是指
certain number of processors you're running.
运作中的处理器的数目
P bar is defined just in terms of
P帽则是要看
the computation you're executing,
你在执行的计算量
not in terms of the machine you're running it on.
而不是你的处理器
OK, it's just the average amount of work
好的 它就是关键路径上
that can be done in parallel
能够并行执行的
along each step of the critical path.
功的平均分量
OK, questions so far?
好的 还有问题吗？
So mostly we're just doing definitions so far.
目前 我们只是下了定义
OK, now we get into,
接下来是深入
OK, so it's helpful to know what the parallelism is,
它有助于我们理解什么是并行度
because the parallelism is going to,
因为并行度就是
there's no real point in trying to
你是不可能...
get speed up bigger than the parallelism.
获得比并行度更快的加速
OK, so if you are given a particular computation,
好的 所以如果给定一个计算
you'll be able to say, oh, it doesn't go any faster.
你可能会说 噢 怎么没有变得更快？
You're throwing more processors at it.
你投入了很多的处理器
Why is it that going any faster?
但为什么它不能变得更快？
And the answer could be, no more parallelism.
答案可能是 并行化到顶了
OK, let's see what I want to,
抱歉导演 我忘词了
yeah, I think we can raise the example here.
想起来了 我们这里可以举个例子
We'll talk more about this model.
我们再谈谈这个模型
Mostly, now, we're going to just talk about DAG's.
现在 我们集中讨论DAG
So, we'll talk about the programming model next time.
那么 我们下一次再来讨论编程模型
So, let's talk about scheduling.
好 我们来研究调度算法
The goal of scheduler is
调度的目的是
to map the computation to P processors.
将计算分配到P个处理器上
And this is typically done by a runtime system,
而且这通常是由一个运行时系统完成
which, if you will, is an algorithm that
也就是我即将展示的
is running underneath the language layer that I showed you.
在语言层下面运作的算法
OK, so the programmer designs
好的 程序员设计了
an algorithm using spawns, and syncs, and so forth.
使用衍生、同步指令的算法
Then, underneath that, there's an algorithm that has to
然而在底层 这个算法需要
actually map that executing program
在实际运行中 将程序映射到
onto the processors of the machine as it executes.
计算机的处理器上
And that's the scheduler.
这就是调度算法
OK, so it's done by the language runtime system, typically.
这一般是由编程语言的运行时系统来完成
OK, so it turns out that online schedulers,
实际上 在线调度算法
let me just say they're complex.
可以说很复杂
OK, they're not necessarily easy things to build.
它们肯定不是课后习题那种级别的
OK, they're not too bad actually.
但它们实际上也不可怕
But, we are not going to go there
只是我们也不打算讲
because we only have two lectures to do this.
因为我们只有两节课的时间讲多线程
Instead, we're going to do is
取而代之 我们准备讲的
we'll illustrate the ideas using off-line scheduling.
是阐述离线调度的思想
OK, so you'll get an idea
你们会从中了解
out of this for what a scheduler does,
调度算法的任务是什么
and it turns out that doing these things online is
你会发现 要把这些任务在线完成
another level of complexity beyond that.
复杂度将会是骨灰级的
And typically, the online schedulers
而典型 在线调度算法
that are good these days, are randomized schedulers.
目前比较强势的 是随机调度算法
And they have very strong proofs
它有些强大的证明
of their ability to perform.
来证明它们的强大
But we're not going to go there.
但是我们不准备讲那些
We'll keep it simple.
节约脑细胞
And in particular, we're going to look at
但我们会特别留意一种
a particular type of scheduler called a greedy scheduler.
叫做贪心调度的调度算法
So, if you have a DAG to execute,
如果你有一个要执行的DAG
so the basic rules of the scheduler is
那调度算法的基本规则是
you can't execute a node until all of the nodes
只要DAG图中某一结点的前者没执行完
that precede it in the DAG have executed.
你都不能执行那个节点
OK, so you've got to wait until everything is executed.
所以 你要等到前面所有点都完成才行
So, a greedy scheduler, what it says is let's just
那么 这种贪心调度算法说
try to do as much as possible on every step, OK?
不如每一步都尽可能多做一点吧？
In other words, it says I'm never going to try to
换句话说 它从不理会
guess that it's worthwhile delaying doing something.
延迟下一步到底值不值得
If I could do something now, I'm going to do it.
要活在当下
And so, each step is going to
而每一步
correspond to be one of two types.
又分别对应两种类型
The first type is what we'll call a complete step.
第一种 就是我们所说的完整步骤
And this is a step in which
这样的步骤里
there are at least P threads ready to run.
至少有P个线程准备运行
And, I'm executing on P processors.
而我则会用P个处理器来执行
So, what's a greedy strategy here?
那么 这里的贪心策略是什么？
I've got P processors. I've got at least P threads.
我有P个处理器 也有至少P个线程
Run any P. Yeah, first P would be
跑任意P个线程  第一批P线程
if you had a notion of ordering.
如果你有顺序强迫症的话
That would be perfectly reasonable.
那将会非常有意义
Here, we are just going to execute any P.
但这里 我们将运行任意的P个线程
We might make a mistake there,
虽然我们可能犯了一个错误
because there may be a particular one that
因为可能有一个是特别的线程
if we execute now,
如果先运行的话
that'll enable more parallelism later on.
后面可能会带来更多的并行度
We might not execute that one. We don't know.
我们可能会错过那一个 因为我们不知道
OK, but basically, what we're going to do
但基本上 我们要做的
is just execute any P willy-nilly. So, there's some,
是不管三七二十一地运行任意P  所以的话
if you will, non-determinism in this step here
如果你这样做 会带来一些不决定因素
because which one you execute
因为你执行操作
may or may not be a good choice.
不一定是个好选择
OK, the second type of step we're going to have
第二种我们要说的步骤类型是
is an incomplete step. And this is a situation
不完整步骤  这种情况里
where we have fewer than P threads ready to run.
我们有少于P个的线程要运行
So, what's our strategy there?
那这里要用什么策略？
Execute all of them. OK, if it's greedy,
把它们全执行了就好 贪婪算法嘛
no point in not executing.
啥都不干就没意义了
OK, so if I've got more than P threads ready to run,
如果我有多于P个线程要运行
I execute any P.
我就运行P个
If I have fewer than P threads ready to run,
如果我有少于P个线程要运行
we execute all of them.
我就把所有线程都运行了
So, it turns out this is a good strategy.
这实际上是一个很好的策略
It's not a perfect strategy. In fact, the strategy of
虽然不是完美的 但实际上
trying to schedule optimally a DAG on P processors
要是想把DAG最完美地调度到P个处理器上
is NP complete, meaning it's very difficult.
是NP完全问题  也就是说 别想了
So, those of you going to take 6.045 or 6.840,
打个广告 你们去上6.045和6.840的课吧
I highly recommend these courses,
强烈推荐
and we'll talk more about that in the last lectures
最后一节课上 我们会更深入讨论
we talked a little bit about
我们会再谈谈
what's coming up in the theory engineering concentration.
未来的理论和工程的发展重心
You can learn about NP completeness
你们会学习NP完全问题
and about how you show that certain problems,
以及如何证明这些问题
there are no good algorithms for them,
找不到一个好的算法解决
OK, that we are aware of,
我们会意识到这些
OK, and what exactly that means.
还有它究竟代表了什么
So, it turns out that
那实际上
this type of scheduling problem turns out
这种调度问题原来
to be a very difficult problem to get it optimal.
是一个非常难以优化的复杂问题
But, there's nice theorem,
但也有个很不错的定理
due independently to Graham and Brent.
分别由Graham和Brent独立提出
It says, essentially,
这个定理说 基本上
a greedy scheduler executes any computation G,
一个贪婪调度算法执行任意计算G
with work, T_1, and critical path length T_∞
若功为T_1 关键路径长为T_∞
in time T_P, less than or equal to T_1 over P plus T_∞
那它的运行时间T_P ≤ T_1/P + T_∞
on a computer with P processors.
这是P个处理器的情况
OK, so, it says that
这就是说
I can achieve T_1 over P plus T_∞
我可以取得T_1/P + T_∞
So, what does that say?
这又说明什么？
If we take a look and compare this
如果我们仔细观察对比
with our lower bounds on runtime, how efficient is this?
与我们运行时的下界相比 这个的效率如何？
How does this compare with the optimal execution?
这跟最优的执行时间相比如何？
Yeah, it's two competitive.
对了 这是双竞争的
It's within a factor of two of optimal
它在最优时间的两倍以内
because this is a lower bound
因为这是一个下界
and this is a lower bound.
这也是一个下界
And so, if I take twice the max of these two,
所以 取这两者中的最大值的两倍
twice the maximum of these two,
两倍于这两者的最大值
that's going to be bigger than the sum.
它比这个和要大
So, I'm within a factor of two
所以 T_P在任意情况下
of which ever is the stronger lower bound for any situation.
都小于等于 两个下界中更强那个的两倍
So, this says you get within a factor
所以它说 你得到的是
of two of efficiency of scheduling
在P处理器运行时中
in terms of the runtime on P processors.
两倍以内的最优调度时间
OK, does everybody see that?
你们都清楚了吗？
So, let's prove this theorem.
那我们来证明这个定理吧
It's quite an elegant theorem.
这是一个很优雅的定理
It's not a hard theorem. One of the nice things,
这个定理不难 这也是一个优点
by the way, about this week,
另外 这星期的课
is that nothing is very hard.
没有什么特别难的
It just requires you to think differently.
只需要你们从不同角度思考
OK, so the proof has to do with counting up
好的 证明需要数一数
how many complete steps we have,
我们共有多少完整步骤
and how many incomplete steps we have.
又有多少不完整步骤
OK, so we'll start with the number of complete steps.
我们先来数完全步骤的数目
So, can somebody tell me what's the largest number
谁能告诉我 我们可能取得的
of complete steps I could possibly have?
最大的完整步骤数目是多少？
Yeah, I heard somebody mumble it back there.
我听到了真理的低吟
T_1 over P. Why is that?
T_1/P  为什么是它？
Yeah, so the number of complete steps is, at most,
是的 完整步骤的数目 它的最大值
T_1 over P because why?
为什么是T_1/P
[Student]：......
[学生]:
Yeah, once you've had this many, you've done T_1 work, OK?
没错 一旦你做完这么多步 你就做完T_1的功了
So, every complete step I'm getting P work done.
因为每一步完整步骤我都做了P的功
So, if I did more than T_1 over P steps,
如果我做了T_1/P步
there would be no more work to be done.
那就没哟多余的功要做了
So, the number of complete steps
所以 完整步骤的数目
can't be bigger than T_1 over P.
不可能比T_1/P大
OK, so that's this piece.
这个是完整步骤
OK, now we're going to count up the incomplete steps,
现在我们来数不完整步骤
and show its bounded by T infinity.
证明它是以T_∞为界
OK, so let's consider an incomplete step.
我们来考虑一个不完整步骤
And, let's see what happens. And, let's let G prime be
看看会发生什么 我们令G’为
the subgraph of G that remains to be executed.
G的其中一个要被执行的子图
OK, so we'll draw a picture here.
那我们来画个图
So, imagine we have,
假设我们有
let's draw it on a new board.
画在另一块板上吧
So here, we're going to have a graph, our graph, G.
这里 我们要画一幅图 我们的图G
We're going to do actually P
我们这里设P的值为
equals three as our example here.
这里就设 P=3 吧
So, imagine that this is the graph, G.
试想这就是图G
And, I'm not showing the procedures here
我不在这里列举详细的步骤了
because this actually is a theorem that works for any DAG.
因为这个定理对所有DAG都有效
And, the procedure outlines are not necessary.
没有必要列举课程详细了
All we care about is the threads.
我们关注的是线程
I missed one. OK, so imagine that's my DAG, G
我漏了个 好的 想象这是我们的DAG G
and imagine that I have executed up to this point.
再想象我已经执行到这一点了
Which ones have I executed?
我之前执行了哪些？
Yeah, I've executed these guys.
对了 我执行的是这些
So, the things that are in G prime are just the things
所以说 在G'里面的东西
that have yet to be executed.
都还没被执行过
And these guys are the ones that are already executed.
这些是已经运作过的
And, we'll imagine that all of them
然后 我们假设他们全部
are unit time threads without loss of generality.
都是单位时间线程 使其不失一般性
The theorem would go through, even if each of these
所以这个定理是通用的 即使每一个结点
had a particular time associated with it.
可能都有一个特定的执行时间
The same scheduling algorithm will work just fine.
用相同的调度算法也没问题
So, how can I characterize the threads
那我要怎么区分
that are ready to be executed?
那些即将要执行的线程呢？
Which are the threads
这里有哪些线程
that are ready to be executed here?
是即将要执行的？
Let's just see. So, that one?
我们看看  这个吗？
No, that's not ready to be executed. Why?
不不  还没轮到这个
Because it's got a predecessor here, this guy.
因为它之前还有一个结点
OK, so this guy is ready to be executed,
好的 这个才是即将执行的那个
and this guy is ready to be executed.
还有这个也即将执行
OK, so those two threads are ready to be,
那好 这两个线程即将要执行
how can I characterize this?
我怎么区分它们？
What's their property?
它们有什么性质？
What's a graph theoretic property in G prime that tells me
这个图G’有着什么样的性质 能让我分辨出
whether or not something is ready to be executed?
一个结点是否准备执行？
It has no predecessor,
没有前任结点
but what's another way of saying that?
换句话说 是什么性质？
It's got no predecessor in G prime.
如果在图G’里没有前任结点
What does it mean for a node
对于一个节点来说
not to have a predecessor in a graph?
在途中没有前任结点是什么意思？
Its in degree is zero, right? Same thing.
它的入度为0 是吧？意思是一样的
So, the threads with in-degree zero in G prime
那么在图G’中 入度为0的线程
are the ones that are ready to be executed.
就是即将要被执行的线程
OK, and if it's incomplete step, what do I do?
那对于不完整步骤 我要怎么做？
I'm going to execute says,
那我执行的就是...
if it's an incomplete step, I execute all of them.
如果是不完整步骤 我就把它们全执行了
OK, so I execute all of these.
我把它们全都执行了
OK, now when I execute all of the in-degree zero threads,
当我执行所有入度为0的线程时
what happens to the critical path length of the graph
图中接下来要执行的关键路径
that remains to be executed?
又会有什么变化？
It decreases by one.
会减1
So the critical path length of what remains to be executed
所以 接下来G'要执行的关键路径
of G prime, is reduced by one.
就要减去1
So, what's left to be executed on every incomplete step,
每一次不完整步骤所剩下的关键路径
what's left to be executed always reduces by one.
它的长度总是要减1
Notice the next step here is going to be a complete step,
注意了 这里的下一步是个完整步骤
because I've got four things that are ready to go.
因为我有四个即将执行的结点
And, I can execute them in such a way
在某些执行情况里
that the critical path length
图的关键路径长度
doesn't get reduced on that step.
不会因此而减少
OK, but if I had to execute all of them,
但如果能把所有结点都执行了的话
then it does reduce the critical path length.
它也会减少关键路径的长度
Now, of course, both could happen, OK, at the same time,
当然了 同一时间里 两种情况都可能发生
OK, but any time that I have an incomplete step,
但只要我有不完全步骤
I'm guaranteed to reduce the critical path length by one.
我就肯定会减少关键路径的长度
OK, so that implies that the number of incomplete steps is,
这就意味着 不完全步骤的数目
at most, T infinity. And so, therefore,
最大为T_∞  因此
T of P is, at most, the number of complete steps
T_P就等于 完全步骤的数目
plus the number of incomplete steps.
加上不完全步骤的数目
And we get our bound.
所以我们得到了上界
This is sort of an amortized argument
这也算是一种平摊分析吧
if you want to think of it that way,
你可以这样认为
OK, that at every step
在每一步中
I'm either amortizing the step against the work,
我或者是对功做平摊
or I'm amortizing it against the critical path length,
又或者是对关键路径长度做平摊
or possibly both.
又或者两者都有
But I'm at least doing one of those for every step,
但我至少在每一步都做了其中一项
OK, and so, in the end,
所以最终
I just have to add up the two contributions.
我只需要把这两项相加就好了
Any questions about that? So this, by the way,
有没有什么问题？  顺便说下
is the fundamental theorem of all scheduling.
这个是所有调度算法的基础
If ever you study anything having to do with scheduling,
如果你以后还要学习调度算法
this basic result is sort of
这个基础的结论
the foundation of a huge number of things.
就是之后所有理论的基础
And then what people do is they gussy it up,
人们的工作就是在此之上不断升华
like, let's do this online, OK, with a scheduler, etc.,
比如 在用到在线调度算法等的时候
that everybody's trying to match these bounds,
人们都会尝试去达到这个上界
OK, of what an omniscient greedy scheduler would achieve,
这个无敌的贪婪调度算法的上界
OK, and there are all kinds of other things.
你们会学到很多很多理论
But this is sort of the basic theorem
但这就是基础的部分
that just pervades the whole area of scheduling.
它是调度领域里的真理
OK, let's do a quick corollary.
我们快速地来做个推论
I'm not going to erase those.
这些我就不擦了
Those are just too important. I want to erase those.
那些内容太重要了 我擦这些吧
Let's not erase those. I don't want to erase that either
这些也不能擦 好纠结啊
We can go back to the top.
我们还是回到上面吧
Actually, we'll put the corollary here
算了 我还是把推论写在这里
because that's just one line. OK.
因为这只有一行而已
The corollary says you get linear speed up
这个推论说 你的加速是线性的
if the number of processors that you allocate,
如果你投入到运行中的处理器
that you run your job on is order, the parallelism.
是以并行度为阶的话
So greedy scheduler gives you linear speed up if you're
所以 贪婪调度算法能给你带来线性的加速
running on essentially parallelism or fewer processors.
如果你的处理器数量是等于或少于并行度的话
OK, so let's see why that is.
我们来分析下为什么
And I hope I'll fit this, OK?
希望这里能写得下
So, P bar is T_1 over T infinity.
所以 P帽等于T_1/T_∞
And that implies that
这隐含了
if P equals order T_1 over T infinity,
如果P是O（T_1/T_∞）的话
then that says just bringing those around,
那么我们移个项
T infinity is order T_1 over P. So, everybody with me?
得出T_∞=O（T_1/P） 大家看懂没？
It's just algebra.
这是代数运算
So, it says this is the definition of parallelism,
这个是并行度的定义
T_1 over T infinity, and so,
T_1/T_∞
if P is order parallelism,
如果P是并行度阶的
then it's order T_1 over T infinity.
也就是O（T_1/T_∞）
And now, just bring it around.
现在 我们来移个项
It says T infinity is order T_1 over P.
变成T_∞等于O（T_1/P）
So, that says T infinity is order T_1 over P.
推出T_∞等于O（T_∞）
OK, and so, therefore, continue the proof here,
那么因此 我们在这边继续证明
thus T_P is at most T_1 over P plus T infinity.
因为 T_P最大为T_1/P + T_∞
Well, if this is order T_1 over P,
s所以说 如果这也是T_1/P阶的话
the whole thing is order T_1 over P.
那么整个东西就也是T_1/P
OK, and so, now I have T_P is order T_1 over P,
好的 我现在有T_P是O(T_1/P)的
and what we need is to compute T_1 over T_P,
我们再来计算下T_1/T_P
and that's going to be order T_p. Ok?
这就等于O(P)
Does everybody see that?
大家看懂没？
So what that says is that
这也就是说
if I have a certain amount of parallelism,
如果我有一定量的并行度
if I run essentially on
如果我投入了
fewer processors than that parallelism,
恰好少于并行度的处理器
I get linear speed up if I use greedy scheduling.
我用贪婪调度就能得到线性的加速
OK, if I run on more processors than the parallelism,
如果我投入的处理器比并行度要多
in some sense I'm being wasteful
我就可能浪费了
because I can't possibly get enough speed up
因为我投入的额外的处理器
to justify those extra processors.
并不能给我带来加速效果
So, understanding parallelism of a job says
所以 一项任务的并行度可以理解为
that's sort of a limit
是一个极限
on the number of processors I want to have.
处理器数量的极限
And, in fact, I can achieve that.
实际上 我可以到达这个极限
Question?
什么问题？
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Prof]：Yeah, really, in some sense,
[教授]:没错 某种意义上
this is saying it should be omega P.
这应该是Ω(P)才对
Yeah, so that's fine.
不过还好
It's a question of, so ask again.
这个问题是... 请继续说
[Student]：......
[学生]:......
[Prof]：No, it's only if it's bounded above by a constant.
[教授]:不不 仅当它有一个常数上界
T_1 and T infinity aren't constants.
但T_1和T_∞并不是常数
They're variables in this.
在这里 它们是常数
So, we are doing multivariable asymptotic analysis.
我们这里是在做多变量的渐近分析
So, any of these things can be
这里讨论的东西都可能
a function of anything else,
与别的东西有函数关系
and can be growing as much as we want.
都可能符合我们预期的增长
So, the fact that we say
我们说
we are given it for a particular thing,
给定某一个东西
we're really not given that number.
我们不是真的给定一个数字
We're given a whole class of DAG's
我们是给定一整套的DAG图
or whatever of various sizes
不管什么大小也好
is really what we're talking about.
这才是我们讨论的东西
So, I can look at the growth.
这样我才能看清它的增长率
Here, where it's talking about
我们这里讨论的
the growth of the parallelism,
是并行度的增长率
sorry, the growth of the runtime T_P
抱歉 是运行时间T_P的增长率
as a function of T_1 and T infinity.
它是关于T_1和T_∞的函数值
So, I am talking about things that are growing here, OK?
我们讨论的是这个的增长率 好吧？
OK, so let's put this to work, OK?
好的 我们开始来证明
And, in fact, so now I'm going to go back to here.
实际上...我要回来这边写
Now I'm going to tell you about
现在我要给你们讲讲
a little bit of my own research,
我自己的一些研究
and how we use this in some of the work that we did.
还有我是怎样把它应用到我的工作中去
OK, so we've developed a dynamic multithreaded language
我们开发了一种动态多线程语言
called Cilk,  spelled with a C
叫做Cilk 以C打头
because it's based on the language, C.
以为这是基于C开发的
And, it's not an acronym
它不是一个缩写词哦
because cilk is like nice threads,
因为丝绸是好的线嘛
OK, although at one point my students had a competition
曾经我的学生有过华山论"线"
for what the acronym cilk could mean.
讨论Cilk是什么的缩写
The winner, turns out,
但得出结果却是
was Charles' Idiotic Linguistic Kluge.
“错爱理科”
So anyway, if you want to take a look at it,
反正我是信了 如果你了解过它
you can find some stuff on it here.
你就能发现其中的一些东西
OK, and what it uses is actually
它实际上用到了
one of these more complicated schedulers.
这些超复杂的调度算法中的一个
It's a randomized online scheduler,
是一种随机在线调度算法
OK, and if you look at
如果你看到
its expected runtime on P processors,
它在P个处理器上跑的预期时间
it gets effectively
它实际上
T_1 over P plus O of T infinity provably.
可以证明是T_1/P + O(T_∞)
OK, and empirically,
经验告诉我们
if you actually look at what kind of runtimes you get
如果你真要通过运行时间
to find out what's hidden in the big O there,
以此来调查大O所隐含的算式
it turns out, in fact, it's T_1 over P plus T infinity
其实你会发现 T_P约等于T_1/P + T_∞
with the constants here being very close to one empirically
从经验来看 T_∞的常数因子非常接近1
So, no guarantees,
虽然不能保证
but this turns out to be a pretty good bound.
但这一条式真的是一个非常好的上界
Sometimes, you see a coefficient on T infinity
你有时候会发现T_∞的系数的大小
that's up maybe close to four or something.
可能接近4神马的
But generally, you don't see something
但一般来说 它都不会
that's much bigger than that.
比4更大了
And mostly, it tends to be around,
大多数情况下 它大概就是那么多
if you do a linear regression curve fit,
如果你做个线性回归的曲线拟合
you get that the constant here is close to one.
你就会求出 这个常数为1
And so, with this,
那么 有了这个
you get near perfect if you use this formula
如果用这条式来做你的运算时间模型
as a model for your runtime.
就近乎完美了
You get near perfect linear speed up
你将获得几乎完美的线性加速
if the number of processors you're running on is
如果你运行的处理器的数量
much less than your average parallelism,
远小于你的平均并行度的话
which, of course,
当然了
is the same thing as if T infinity
如果T_∞远小于T_1/P
is much less than T_1 over P.
结果也一样
So, what happens here is that
那么 这里的意思就是
when P is much less than P infinity, that is,
当P远小于P_∞时 又或者
T infinity is much less than T_1 over P,
T_∞远小于T_1/P
this term ceases to matter very much,
这一项就变得不重要了
and you get very good speedup,
然后你的加速就很好
OK, in fact, almost perfect speedup.
好的 事实上 几乎是线性的
So, each processor gives you another processor's work
这种情况下 每个处理器都会发挥到作用
as long as you are the range
只要总的处理器数量
where the number of processors
还在这个范围里
is much less than the number of parallelism.
就是远小于并行度这个范围
Now, with this language many years ago,
现在 这个语言多年以前
which seems now like many years ago,
你们还在打酱油的时候
OK, it turned out we competed.
就已经很强势了
We built a bunch of chess programs.
我们写了一堆象棋程序
And, among our programs were Starsocrates and Cilkchess
比如说有"苏格拉底之星"和"Cilk象棋"
and we also had several others.
还有一些别的
And these were, I would call them, world-class.
这些程序都已经是棋灵王的境界了
In particular, we tied for first
说到我们的辉煌史
in the 1995 World Computer Chess Championship in Hong Kong,
我们是1995年象棋世锦赛香港站的第一
and then we had a playoff and we lost.
但后来再复赛中惜败了
It was really a shame.
惜败的惜啊
We almost won, running on a big parallel machine.
我们差点就用并行计算机征服象棋界了
That was, incidentally, some of you may know
可能你们曾经听说过
about the Deep Blue chess playing program.
IBM的"深蓝"象棋程序
That was the last time
那次香港的比赛
before they faced then world champion Kasparov
是它在跟世界冠军Kasparov对战前
that they competed against programs.
最后一次跟机器的对弈
They tied for third in that tournament.
它那次才只是第三而已
OK, so we actually out-placed them.
所以说我们更虎一点
However, in the head-to-head competition,
虽然说 在一对一单挑的时候
we lost to them.
我们输了
So we had one loss in the tournament
我们直到决赛时都还是
up to the point of the finals.
只尝一败
They had a loss and a draw.
它们一负一平
Most people aren't aware that Deep Blue, in fact,
很多人都觉得深蓝实际上
was not the reigning World Computer Chess Championship
还不够资格作为世界冠军的对手
when they faced Kasparov.
毕竟是Kasparov大神
The reason that they faced Kasparov
它可以跟大神进行对战
was because IBM was willing to put up the money.
完全是因为土豪IBM舍得扔钱
OK, so we developed these chess programs,
所以 我们开发了一个象棋程序
and the way we developed them,
我们的开发之路是
let me in particular talk about Starsocrates.
我要好好讲讲"苏格拉底之星"
We had this interesting anomaly come up.
我们有个很有趣的异常状况
We were running on
我们当时用了
a 32 processor computer at MIT for development.
MIT的32核的计算机来开发
And, we had access to a 512 processor computer
后来我们用的是512核的机子
for the tournament at NCSA at the University of Illinois.
伊利诺斯大学那的国家超级计算机 去参加比赛
So, we had this big machine.
我们有这么一个大机子
Of course, they didn't want to give it to us very much,
虽然他们不是很想借给我们
but we have the same machine, just a small one, at MIT.
但我们在MIT也有一个相对小点的机子
So, we would develop on this,
我们就在这上面开发
and occasionally we'd be able to run on this,
有时我们又可以在这上面跑
and this was what we were developing for on our processor.
而最后的竞赛就是我们开发的目标
So, let me show you sort of the anomaly that came up, OK?
那么 我来告诉你们有什么异常情况发生了吧
So, we had a version of a program
我们的程序有个版本
that I'll call the original program,
我们称之为原始程序
OK, and we had an optimized program
因为后来我们有优化程序
that included some new features
加了一些新特性进去
that were supposed to make the program go faster.
它理论上应该跑得更快些
And so, we timed it on our 32 processor machine.
所以 我们给原始程序在32核的机子上计时
And, it took us 65 seconds to run it.
用了我们65秒
OK, and then we timed this new program.
用新程序计时的话
So, I'll call that T prime of sub 32
把它叫做T'_32
on our 32 processor machine,
鉴于我们用的是32核
and it ran and 40 seconds
它跑了40秒
to do this particular benchmark.
来完成我们的一个基准测试
Now, let me just say, I've lied about
好吧 我承认我撒谎了
the actual numbers here to make the calculations easy.
实际数字不好计算 我简化了下
But, the same idea happened.
但意思是一样的
Just the numbers were messier.
只是数字有点出入
OK, so this looks like
这看上去应该
a significant improvement in runtime,
是一个重要的改进
but we rejected the optimization.
但我们否决了这个优化
OK, and the reason we rejected it
我们否决的原因
is because we understood
是因为我们知道
about the issues of work and critical path.
功和关键路径的事
So, let me show you the analysis that we did,
我来讲讲当时的分析
OK? So the analysis,
分析就是
it turns out, if we looked at our instrumentation,
其实 如果我们观察我们的指标
the work in this case was 2,048.
在对于原程序 功是2048
And, the critical path was one second,
关键路径是1秒
which, over here with the optimized program,
而这边的优化程序
the work was, in fact, 1,024.
功是1024
But the critical path was eight.
但关键路径是8
So, if we plug into our simple model here,
如果我们把它带入我们的简单模型
the one I have up there with the approximation there,
我们上面这个 有近似步骤的那个模型
I have T_32 is equal to T_1 over 32 plus T infinity,
我们有T_32等于T_1/32+T_∞
and that's equal to,
那就等于
well, the work is 2,048 divided by 32.
功是2048除以32
What's that?
那是多少？
64, good, plus the critical path, one, that's 65.
64 好的 再加上关键路径 那就是65
So, that checks out with what we saw.
这跟我们看到的事实吻合
OK, in fact, we did that,
真的 我们的确做到了
and it checked out.
而且确实吻合
OK, it was very close. OK, over here,
非常非常接近 所以这边
T prime of 32 is T prime one over 32,
T'_32就是T'_1/32
plus T infinity prime,
加上T'_∞
and that's equal to 1,024 divided by 32 is 32
这就等于1024除以32 就是32
plus eight, the critical path here. That's 40.
再加上8的关键路径 所以是40
So, that checked out too.
这个也吻合
So, now what we did is we said
那么现在我们说
OK, let's extrapolate to our big machine.
我们来看看在超级计算机上如何吧
How fast are these things going to run on our big machine?
这些东西在超级计算机上跑得有多快？
Well, for that, we want T of 512.
那这次 我们有T_512
And, that's equal to T_1 over 512 plus T infinity.
它等于T_1/512+T_∞
And so, what's 2,048 divided by 512?
所以说 2048/512
It's four, plus T infinity is one.
等于4 加上T_∞ 也就是1
That's equal to five.
一共为5
So, go quite a bit faster on this.
我们这次算的真的很快
But here, T prime of 512 is equal to T one prime over 512
而这边 T'_514等于T'_1/512
plus T infinity prime is equal to,
再加上T’_∞  就等于
well, 1,024 plus divided by 512
我算算 1024除以512
is two plus critical path of eight, that's ten.
等于2 再加上关键路径8 就是10
OK, and so, you see that on the big machine,
那么 你可以看到在大机子上
we would have been running
我们的优化
twice as slow had we adopted that,
比原程序还要慢一倍
quote, "Optimization",
这就是所谓的"优化"
OK, because we had run out of parallelism,
因为我们的并行度已经用尽了
and this was making the critical path longer.
而这个却增加了关键路径
We needed to have a way of doing it
我们需要一种方法
where we could reduce the work.
来减少我们的功
Yeah, it's good to reduce the work
确实 它减少了很多
but not if the critical path
但关键路径却变长了
ends up getting rid of the parallelism
使得程序的并行化
that we hope to be able to use during the runtime.
变得远离了我们希望做到的目标
So, it's twice as slow, OK, twice as slow.
整整慢了一倍 一倍啊亲
So the moral is that the work and critical path length
这个道理告诉我们 功和关键路径长度
predict the performance better than the execution time alone
对于性能的预测比单单运行时间要好
OK, when you look at scalability.
因为你需要可扩展性
And a big issue on a lot of these machines is scalability;
这些机器的可扩展性是一个大问题
not always, sometimes you're not worried about scalability.
虽然不是经常 但你有时不需要考虑到它
Sometimes you just care.
有时你就在乎
Had we been running in the competition
如果我们在比赛中
on a 32 processor machine,
用的是32核的机子
we would have accepted this optimization.
我们就会接受这个优化
It would have been a good trade-off.
这是一个不错的权衡条件
OK, but because we knew that we were
但因为我们知道
running on a machine with a lot more processors,
我们要在一个更多处理器的机子上跑
and that we were close to running out of the parallelism,
我们几乎把并行度都用光了
it didn't make sense to be
这样的话
increasing the critical path at that point,
增加关键路径长度就很不科学
because that was just reducing
这样就减少了
the parallelism of our calculation.
我们运算的并行度
OK, next time,
好的 下次课
any questions about that first? No?
先问问还有没有问题？
OK. Next time, now that we understand
好的 下次课 现在我们了解了
the model for execution,
运算执行的模型
we're going to start looking at
下一步我们将看看
the performance of particular algorithms
一些特定算法的性能
what we code them up in a dynamic, multithreaded style,
我们将会用动态多线程的风格来改写它们
[student]Inaudible
[学生]:...